<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of Italy or, The Italian anatomiz'd.  / by An English chyrurgion.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B18912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E.2109[3]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868920</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868920</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B18912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 241:E2109[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of Italy or, The Italian anatomiz'd.  / by An English chyrurgion.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 93, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Brooke at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf bears the printer's device of Nathaniel Brooke on verso.</note>
                  <note>With three final pages of advertisements.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Racism --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Italy --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Italy --  Description and travel --  1501-1800 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF ITALY: Or, The Italian Anatomiz'd BY <hi>An Engliſh Chyrurgion.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Diſſicile eſt Saty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am non ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere.—</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Brooke</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THat this <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> ſhould ſuit with the Grain of all Mens Diſpoſitions, is far beyond my expectation; becauſe I am ſufficiently ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that Mens mindes are as diſcrepant, as their Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiognomies are various: And it hath been the fate of all
<pb facs="tcp:121277:3"/>Writers that ever appeared in publique, (eſpecially un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts) to be attended by ſome carping <hi>Zoilus:</hi> But fall back fall edge, I will be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a ſufficient ſtock of Patience to undergo the Succeſs of this Publication. I know already, that if ſome carping Critick light on it, he will caſt it aſide, and ſay, theſe Whimſies are but <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genii laſcivientis floſculi,</hi> the ſuperfluous Excreſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of laſciviating wit. Or probably ſome Squeamiſh Zealot, who through Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocondraick Melancholy, is
<pb facs="tcp:121277:3"/>become a meer Lump of quickened Care, may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt it; yet the more frol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickiſh Genius, who no doubt is freer from intended miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief then the thoughtful man, will diſgeſt it.</p>
            <p>Let not the ſmallneſs of the bulk occaſion your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; for the more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a thing is, the narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the circumference that contains it. And it is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſaid, <hi>The ſmaller the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, the fewer the faults:</hi> Some there are undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which have either eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Printer, or elſe were occaſioned by my own neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect;
<pb facs="tcp:121277:4"/>but my Sanctuary is the hope of your accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Candor and Clemency, which may ſhrowd me from any falſe imputation: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, here you have it as it is; and as a man takes his wife, ſo muſt you take this Piece, for better for worſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Here you have my Cruſe of Oyl, as well as my Bottle of Vineger; ſome ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Flowers, as well as bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Wormwood: Nor was it my intention in publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Pamphlet to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatter any ſingle perſon; but, like a Fencer in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Show, wave my Sword
<pb facs="tcp:121277:4"/>about, aim at all, and hit none; yet the mildeneſs of the Concluſion will miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the ſeverity of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordium: And the moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Italian will be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to confeſs that I end well, though I began ill, and will vouchſafe to give his <hi>Plaudite</hi> to the Epilogue, though the Prologue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>Now there is none of the Readers ſo illiterate, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, as to be ignorant of that as true, as ancient Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Finis coronat Opus;</hi> which I have taught to ſpeak Engliſh thus:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:5"/>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>If the end crown the Work, as th Proverb ſays,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then a Black-pudding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves double praiſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>For that hath two ends, and ſo have I, as well as two parts; the one Vituperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the other Laudato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>Reader, peruſe it, if thy more weighty Affaires will permit, it is but ſmall, and ſo will put thee to no great Expence either of Money or Time, and if thou gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt any benefit by the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing of it, it will not repent thee of thy peruſal.
<pb facs="tcp:121277:5"/>All that I ſhall ſay to thee at preſent, is onely this, Be charitable in thy Cenſure, and ſo</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:6"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>BE pleaſed to take notice, that there is lately publiſhed an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Book, Entituled,</hi> Adam <hi>in</hi> Eden: <hi>Or, Natures Paradiſe, The Hiſtory of Plants, Fruits, Herbs and Flowers, with their ſeveral Names, whether Greek, Latine, or Engliſh, the places where they grow, their deſcriptions and kindes, their times of flouriſhing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing; as alſo their ſeveral Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natures, Anatomical Proportions, and particular Phyſical Vertues: Together with neceſſary Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Seaſons of Planting, and gathering of our Engliſh Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, with directions how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them in their Compoſition, or otherwiſe. A Piece very uſeful for Phyſicians and Chyrurgions.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121277:6"/>
            <head>THE <hi>CHARACTER</hi> OF ITALY.</head>
            <p>'TIs a Ciſalpine Clod, a Gowty Leg of that Huge Monſter the World, a rotten Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel where the <hi>Ganymed's</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant the <hi>Layſes;</hi> a Neſt of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, the Merdaille of Nations, and the Excrement of the Earth. 'Tis a Hell, whoſe <hi>Cerberus</hi> is a great, old, fat Bear, (the Hoſt of their [Innes] <hi>Oſteria's</hi> I mean,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121277:7"/>which uſually ſtand alone remote from any village, ſo that Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers muſt reſt ſatisfied with the mean accommodation thoſe <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernae</hi> afford; for he that ſeems to diſguſt their feeble <hi>Mineſtra,</hi> may chance to meet with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at his Departure but an <hi>Allegramente</hi> for amends: and if you ſhould menace your Hoſt, he will retort with double inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, knowing that if his <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letto</hi> ſhould decide the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, the next Church is his <hi>Aſylum,</hi> where no Law nor Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence dare attempt him. Pure Saints! that can convert the Church of God into a Den of Thieves, and make his ſacred Manſion a Shrouding-place or Refuge for Aſſaſſines and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers. Beſides, you are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual fear both at Bed &amp; Board,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121277:7"/>by reaſon of thoſe helliſh ſnares they uſually lay to irretiate and maſſacre ſtrangers; ſo that your delight is entombed in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual horror.</p>
            <p>As for the People, they are an execrable reſidue of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> the ſpurious Iſſue of a ſalacious <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> a meer frippery of Bankrupts; his Baſtards that clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the eye-lids of centoculated <hi>Argus.</hi> And ſince they were once preſerv'd from the invaſion of the <hi>Gauls</hi> by Geeſe, they merit praiſe from none but Gozzelings. There are three things that uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deterr men from viſiting this Countrey: The firſt is the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Inquiſition. The ſecond, the execrable Outrages commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Bandito's.</hi> The third, thoſe troubleſom Bedfellows the <hi>Cimici,</hi> Fleas in folio, yet ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121277:8"/>dainty withal, that they will chooſe their fleſh, and cohabit with the faireſt skin; nay, which is worſe, they are very noiſom to the noſtrils of him that deſtroys them. What ſtout Champion can endure the biting or ſting of the <hi>Tarantula,</hi> that kills with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if not remedied; the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof is enough to procure death, were there not a hope of reſurrection from the cure, <hi>viz.</hi> Dancing. But there are Arguments almoſt innumerable of greater ſolidity and weight, than the praementioned: To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in a few (becauſe prolixity is inconſiſtent with a Character) The <hi>Milaneze</hi> will teach you to be Juglers; the <hi>Bolognois,</hi> Liars, the <hi>Venetian,</hi> Hypocrites; the <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> will metamorphoſe you into Satyrs for Luſt; the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121277:8"/>
               <hi>Florentine</hi> inſtructeth in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice of Poyſon; and <hi>Rome</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plungeth you into an impure O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of Idolatry &amp; Superſtition.</p>
            <p>But now let us take a Survey of their ſtately Fabricks and Towns, whoſe native Pens have exalted them to a higher bulk, than ever their Pike-axes inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that firſt dug their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And firſt let us conſider <hi>Rome,</hi> that reputed Miſtreſs of the World, and Metropolis of <hi>Italy,</hi> whoſe Encomiums hath devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more reams of Paper, and drunk up more bottles of Ink, than would repair a decay'd Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, and we ſhall find her to be according to their own Proverb:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nido di tradimento ove ſi cova,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quanto mal hoggi per ilmondo ſi trova.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121277:9"/>
                  <l>A Neſt of Treaſon, where more miſchief's done,</l>
                  <l>Than by all Nations elſe under the Sun.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Rome</hi> that now uſurps the Name, is but her carcaſe or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, her vice being the cauſe of her ruine; which made <hi>Scali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> vent this as bitter as true Jeſt of her, becauſe the wines of <hi>Italy</hi> laſt not long: <hi>Urbem illam eſſe novum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncetum peſsimum veteris vini optimi;</hi> That it was the worſt new vinegar of the beſt old wine: And indeed it is neither founded in <hi>ſuo ſolo,</hi> nor in <hi>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> puriſsimâ &amp; primitivâ puritate.</hi> Once <hi>Rome</hi> was an Hoſpital for maimed Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, now a Spittle of diſeaſed Opinions. Her ſtreets of old did ſhine with triumphing Caeſars and Conſuls in their trophaeal Chariots, now they gliſten with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121277:9"/>the bald pates of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, who lacquey his Petrified Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty riding a Cock-horſe on mens ſhoulders. Heretofore ſhe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained one of the nobleſt and greateſt Gariſons the world could boaſt of; now ſhe ſupports her ſelf by the moſt abominable Stewes that ever the earth bore. Old <hi>Rome</hi> revenged her Affronts with the point of the Sword, but New <hi>Rome</hi> ſteeps her Revenge in a Cup of Poyſon, which clearly manifeſts that old Verſe no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox:
<q>
                  <l>— <hi>Romae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omnia cum liceant, non licet eſſo bonus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>—At <hi>Rome</hi> by haly rood,</l>
                  <l>All things are lawful, except be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good:</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Nay farther hear but what a Character <hi>Mantuanus,</hi> an Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121277:10"/>of their own, beſtows upon her:
<q>
                  <l>—<hi>Petrique domus polluta fluenti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marceſcit luxu; nulla hic arcana revelo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sanctus ager Scurris, venerabilis Ara lynoedis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Servit; honoranda Divum Gany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medibus Aedes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Here Simony and Sodomy, like two impudent Siſters, brazen it in publick, and no one controules them: As to the former, conſider this Satyrical Dyſtick:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vendit Alexander Claves, Alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Christum;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vendere jure potest; emerat ipſe prius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> As for the latter, our Modern times have furniſhed us with too too many inſtances, ſo that we may ſing with the Poet, and have good reaſon to prompt us to it:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121277:10"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nunc caput es ſceloris, qui caput orbis eras.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou that waſt Miſtriſs of the world,</l>
                  <l>Into a Sea of Sin art hurld.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a market, where Sins and Pardons are ſaleable, nay Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities. A Juglers Shop, whoſe Maſter plays finely at faſt and looſe with Oaths and Vows. A Mill, where the blind and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Laity grind for the fat Clergy. A Magazine where more Scripture is ſtored, than ever their Maker inſpired. A Church that depraves the Text, and pins their Faith upon other mens ſleeves. A Slaughter-houſe, where the Butchers bring in all ſorts of perſons, and now and then a Monarch. A woman that hath been a Whore all her youth, and now is turn'd bawd to Sin. In
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121277:11"/>fine, ſhe's a Monopoly of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eneſs, and her Inhabitants wallow in wantonneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety.</p>
            <p>This City that is founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeven hills, is the reſidence of of that ſeven headed <hi>Hydra,</hi> the Pope, and here he doth tyrannize over his ſubmiſſive Vaſſals, far more than ever <hi>Nero</hi> or <hi>Caligula.</hi> He muſt not paſs without a Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick nip, and now I think on't, I could wiſh my pen were dipt in Lye and Gall, that I might laſh him ſufficiently: He it is, yet cauſeth whatſoever he parrot (or if you will have it Anagramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically) praterlike twattles, to paſs for Bullion, and current, though hammer'd in the impure mint of his own Chymaerical Pericranium, and ſpeaks freely whatſoever he thinks without
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121277:11"/>contradictions, ſo that his <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> will countervail, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balance all the <hi>Ergo's</hi> in the World: His tongue is confited in Pepper, and hath pierc'd the ſides of Chriſtendome more ſhrewdly than ever <hi>Mahomets</hi> Sword did: He it is, with his Complices, that maintain Error to get them a maintenance; He dethrones the Deity, and deifies wood and ſtone; yet he is there <hi>Deus in Terris,</hi> The Dagon which they have ſet up; the Idol which they adore, whoſe indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences make his Kitehin ſmoke, by the help of his coadjutars the Jeſuites, that fetch him fuel from moſt parts in Chriſtendom. There is no ſuch Pick-purſe under the Heavens as his fictitious Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; and could mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be as throughly purged as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121277:12"/>their purſes, they would excel the Angels themſelves in purity. Another trick he hath that helps him to hill up his fatal riches, and that is the <hi>Papal Necromancy,</hi> or ſinging and praying for the dead, which doth ſo flux the pocket, that contrary to the current of all Phyloſophy, it makes them cry out, <hi>Datur vacuum.</hi> He it is that plays the Chyrurgion, and his Clergy-men are the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, that exhibit ſo many Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Clyſters to the poor ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people, blinded with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous zeal, that their purſes at length cannot hold out longer, but give up the ghoſt. Not a day paſſeth, but they extract freſh Silver (rare Eccleſiaſtical Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts) from the hot furnace of their Purgatory: And when they find that [Silver] <hi>Luna</hi> ſhines up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121277:12"/>any perſon with her ſilver rays, then is the time of ſinging Maſs, and praying for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Souls; Not a door, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, or window in Purgatory, but 'tis then open, that Souls may have as free a paſſage, and ſwarm forth as thick as Gnats in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust.</hi> Pretty devices to engroſs and monopolize all the wealth to themſelves: But you know the old Proverb, <hi>Malè parta, malè dilabuntur;</hi> Badly come, badly go: witneſs <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, who during his Chairſhip ſcrap'd together ſo much wealth, that his ſon <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> looſing 100000 Crownes one night at Dice, broke out into this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Germanorum tantum haec peccata ſunt:</hi> Theſe are onely the Sins of the Germans; ſo that 'tis evident what the Father gather'd
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121277:13"/>together with a Rake, the Son ſpread abroad with a Fork: So that ſordid Lucre and Gain is practiſed by the Clergy, and thoſe of the higher, as well as of the lower ſphere: nor can there be perpetrated a Crime, how hain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoever it be, but it falls with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of a remedy from his Diſpenſations, provided the Lady <hi>Pecunia</hi> be your <hi>Suada</hi> or <hi>Oratreſs,</hi> verifying that old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Dulcis odor Lucri ex re qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet.</hi> Take this ſtory for inſtance: <hi>Lubin</hi> comes from <hi>Breſſe</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> and was intreated by Friar <hi>Zeno,</hi> to beg his pardon of the Pope for having gelt his Aſs: <hi>Lubin</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it, who being returned, he demanded whether he had done him the prementioned favor; Yes replies he, and to be real with thee, without any farther diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121277:13"/>for a few more <hi>Julio's</hi> there had been a permiſſion for thee to marry thy Aſs, if thou hadſt had any fancy or affection to a four-footed Bedfellow. Had <hi>Castlehaven</hi> been a Catholick, he had kept his head upon his ſhoulders, and not have been executed for his lechery. 'Twas an excellent quip beſtowed on a Pope by a Painter, who had made the face in the Effigies of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſomewhat more red then ordinary; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded the reaſon, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied as tartly as ſuddenly, That they bluſh'd to ſee the wicked lives of their pretended Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. And though I hold it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane <hi>ludere cum ſacris,</hi> yet I judge it recreative <hi>jocari cum fabulis;</hi> and if the Conſiſtory of Cardinals ſhould ſeem to be offended with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121277:14"/>me, if they chance to light upon this piece, I will bid them reflect upon themſelves, and blame the accurſed pen of that more accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Author of the <hi>Pruril Aſinus,</hi> who hath turn'd the ſacred pages into ſcurvy Jeſts, and not onely abuſed them that God hath creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gods on earth, but even the Deity it ſelf: If it were poſſible for the Devil to ſwive a Witch, their mutual copulation could not produce ſuch a horrid Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar, as the Author of thoſe Queries. Whereas were a man diſpoſed to ſport with the holy Writ, he might pick jeſt out of every verſe in the Bible againſt the Pope, and his Romiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: Take a moderate one for inſtance, by way of <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer:</hi> It is demanded why <hi>St. Peter</hi> Wept after his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121277:14"/>denial of Chriſt? <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Not for his own fault, but becauſe his prophetick Soul foreſaw, that his illegitimate ſucceſſors ſhould confeſs the name, but deny the nature of our Saviour, taking him in as it were at the gate, and thruſting him out at the back door: nor indeed can any perſon <hi>qui vel unciolam ſane mentis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat,</hi> that can lay claim but to a ſcruple of rationality, but affirm, that the Pope doth imitate <hi>St. Peter</hi> in nothing but his denial. I was about to inſert here an old latine ſentence, though ſomewhat harſh, and no Ciceronian ſtyle (not but that I durſt becauſe I am man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mitted from the rigor of the <hi>Ferula</hi>) but leſt his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould meet with this piece, and in a holy indignation tear it, and carry it to the Houſe of eaſe,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121277:15"/>and ſo it ſhould <hi>ſcortigare ſedem Apoſtolicam,</hi> bliſter his Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Seat; to prevent which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, leſt that bliſter might turn to a diſeaſe call'd the <hi>Pyles,</hi> incident to the Anus, charity commanded me to omit it. 'Tis worth your obſervation, that the Popes do uſually arrogate to themſelves the names of thoſe Virtues for Sir-names, which they are moſt averſe from; as <hi>Pius, Benedictus, Clemens,</hi> and the like; when as their whole life is but a continued ſeries of villany and barbariſm: So that they have made themſelves a <hi>Ludibrium</hi> to all neighbouring Nations. The Jews laugh at this Eccleſiaſtical Sultan, and his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim of Cardinals, and ſcoff at his golden Legend, and well may it be term'd ſo (not for the purity
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121277:15"/>of the ſubſtance, but for the vaſte heaps of wealth that thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries rake into his Treaſury:) who can but ſmile at their tales of St. <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Hobgoblins</hi> walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Church-yards, and of St. <hi>Anthonies</hi> being in two places at one time: I know a Gentleman of that name that would give much to be endowed with that property, for his ſoul is divided between two Wenches; now were he thus qualified, he might enjoy them both at one and the ſame time. Nor hath the Pope been withſtood by thoſe of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinion onely, but even by thoſe that are of his own brood, and dedicated to the ſame Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; for the City of <hi>Venice</hi> ſtood it out againſt Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, for the priviledge of her Political Government; And
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121277:16"/>the King of <hi>France</hi> after that grand claſh between <hi>Philipe le Bel;</hi> and <hi>Boniface</hi> wrote to him very reſolutely in theſe words; <hi>Que ta treſgrande ſottiſe ſcache;</hi> Let your monſtrous ſottiſhneſs or ſimplicity underſtand, that we are ſubject to none but God; and utterly diſown your Supremacy over us. But I preſume we have ſate long enough in the Porphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chair: And ſince the Ayr of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo contagious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthful that it wants a Clyſter; beſides, all the ink in my pen cannot cure the letters and ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms of the Popedom, we will leave them, and travel to <hi>Naples,</hi> which according to their own Proverb is, <hi>Un Paradiſo piantato da Diavoli,</hi> a Paradiſe peopled with Devils, ſo pleaſant is the place, and ſo vicious the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121277:16"/>Here <hi>Bacchus</hi> hath his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Cellar, and <hi>Veus</hi> exerciſeth her cortine abominations: for it hath been obſerved that in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> at one time there have been regiſtred 30000 Courtizano's; that for paying ſome ſmall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Pope, have had a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation to play at <hi>Stretch-crup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Whipper-ginny, Tick-tack, In and In,</hi> and ſuch unlawful Games as theſe, <hi>cum privilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſque datum ſceleri canimus,</hi> ſaith the Poet: which may very well be appropriated to this Kingdom. 'Tis a place extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly populous and conſequently vicious, ſo that he that deſires to lead a retired life, muſt not pitch his tents here: for as their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens are fill'd with Oranges, ſo their Houſes want not their Lemans. 'Tis a Maxim here, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121277:17"/>Bawdy-houſes are to be tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all their quarters, and 'tis ranked in the number of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, for the profit that accrews to his Holineſs thereby is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, ſo that the true <hi>Campus Veneris</hi> is now found, where the <hi>Campus Martius</hi> ſtood before. 'Tis confeſt that ſhe ſwarms with Nobility, which are ſeen to trot about all day long, as faſt as Peaſe boyling in a pot, but of ſuch ſlender Eſtates, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Aretines</hi> Obſervation, three Marqueſſes were found at once eating Figs off of one tree to keep them from ſtarving: they are ſwell'd and pufft up with large Titles, but their Acres are but few, &amp; their ſubſtance ſmall. Here it was that the <hi>Morbus Gallicus,</hi> as 'tis vulgarly term'd, though more genuinely <hi>Scabies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121277:17"/>Neapolitana,</hi> was firſt known in Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>As for the Inhabitant, he is according to the quality of the Soyl, of a fiery boyling temper, which cauſeth the Spaniard to ride him with a Bit and a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingal; and he hath as many Windmils in his brain, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in his breaſt, as the French, or any other Nation, witneſs thoſe various Innovations: for in two years, ſhe had no leſs than five Kings, and thoſe fetcht out of ſeveral Countries, in ſo much that you ſhall hardly read in any Hiſtory that ever any political Inſtrument was ſo often out of tune, having known popular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions in leſs than four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, and that of <hi>Maſaniello</hi> was the laſt and moſt violent, like a candle burning at both
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121277:18"/>ends, ſo that you would judge the people to be ſo much diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as if they had been ſtung by a worſe <hi>Reptile</hi> than a <hi>Parantula.</hi> 'T was ſtrange that this poor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Fiſherman, with a ſmall handful of boyes arm'd onely with fury and a baſton, ſhould be ſuch a nine days won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and during that interval of time ſhould ride the proud Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan Courſer and ſnaffle him, til he foam'd at the mouth, their Nobility lay then dormant: and this ſame redounds very much to the diſparagement of the Neopolitan Signiors. But to paſs by this, they are born in a Luxurious Countrey, and they are taken to be the greateſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracers of pleaſure, and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of Ladies, and the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent to themſelves of any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121277:18"/>other nation whatſoever: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that no command from the King, can force a Neapolitan Gentleman to march upon any diſigne for three months in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer till the extremity of the heat be over; Lecherous they are beyond meaſure, witneſs the Accuſation of Duke <hi>Offura</hi> Viceroy of <hi>Naples,</hi> after he was Italianated.</p>
            <p>The fifth Article exhibited againſt him, was: That he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the <hi>Marchiones de Campo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latero</hi> publiquely, as his Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, to accompliſh which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, he accuſtomed to ſend the Marquiſs her Husband upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote employments.</p>
            <p>The eighth was, He committed Rapes upon many young Maids and Virgins, and bored a Woman at the very Altar, and had to do
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121277:19"/>with another in the Chancel of St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church, O horrible! Convert the Church into a Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel houſe?</p>
            <p>Ninth, He frequented Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries, not out of devotion, but for recreation, or more ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantly procreation, our of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and ſacrilegious ends.</p>
            <p>Tenth, He made a feaſt of fleſh upon <hi>Maundy Thurſday,</hi> contrary to the Canons to their Holy Mother the Church, and was never obſerv'd to keep faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but feaſting dayes alwaies.</p>
            <p>Eleventh, He made other feaſts for ſome of the Principal Courtiſanos of <hi>Naples,</hi> &amp; that in <hi>Don Pedro de Toledo's</hi> garden, whom he compelled to confeſs with how many Clergy-men they had traded, and commanded an Inventory of their names to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121277:19"/>taken immediatly. Bleſſed ſaints! that diſapprove of lawful matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, but approve of unlawful meretricious actions: it grieves them to ſee ſuch pure Nunnes fleſh, as they do ſomtimes, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reld up in penitential pickle, yet for all the pretended ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Religion, they can break a Lent to ſeed upon them.</p>
            <p>Twelfth, He would often ride abroad in the Coach with <hi>Juana Maria</hi> a Lady of pleaſure, that was as common as a Barbers Chair, no ſooner one was out, but another was in.</p>
            <p>Thirteenth, He had always in his Houſe a Moriſco ſlave, on whom he begat a Baſtard, and ſuffered him to be educated in the Mahume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Superſtition, and after his deceaſe was entombed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121277:20"/>according to the Turkiſh Rites and Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Twentieth, He did innumer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able other acts of obſcenity and wantonneſs, as inviting the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Concubines into his garden, where he had provided as ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous as luſcious a Banquet for them, after which he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to ſtrip themſelves ſtark naked (where 'tis to be obſerved he had a fancy to ſee the naked truth) whil'ſt he with a hollow trunck, ſhet confits at their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked bodies, which they were to take up ſtanding upon their high Chiappins.</p>
            <p>Twenty one, He cauſed a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to ſtrip himſelf ſtark naked, and ſhave his Dutcheſſes <hi>quod ad ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> ſhe being likewiſe naked, and he all the while ſtanding by with a great knife in his hand to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121277:20"/>cut off his privities, if he found any motion in them all the while: a wretched fellow, and egregious Cox-comb, who deſerved to wear a pair of horns that ſhould reach from one end of <hi>Naples</hi> to the other, and that not a condign puniſhment for his crime.</p>
            <p>O old <hi>Rome!</hi> All thy <hi>Floralia,</hi> wanton Feaſts and Games, come far ſhort of thoſe of thy modern iſſue: no <hi>Pagan, Turk, Jew,</hi> nor <hi>Heathen,</hi> (nay, I'le be loth to ſay, Hell it ſelf never enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd ſuch a Smell-ſmock, ſuch a Linnen-lifter, as this ſalacious he-goat, this wanton Satyr, Duke <hi>Oſſuna.</hi> But leſt this diſcourſe ſhould be unwelcome to the chaſte ears of the Reader, wee'l turn our diſcourſe to a more pleaſing ſubject; And begin with the Peaſant, who though he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121277:21"/>all the week in drudgery and ſervility, yet is ſo puft up with vain glory and pride, that on Sunday and Holy-days, he will be ſure to have his body well cloath'd, though his belly want furniſhing; and his Wife, that works day and night for a hungry living, will be ſo pranked up, that if you were unacquainted with the phantaſtique humor of this mimical people, you would mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake this <hi>Joan,</hi> for ſome Lady of repute, and honor in the country: And indeed they are all ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceited of their deferts, from the Cedar to the ſhrub, with their imaginary Revenues, and the Chimera's that they hatch in their brains of their own dignity and <hi>Grandeza,</hi> that there is not one of them but will ſpeak thouſands, rather then betray
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121277:21"/>their indigency: One will ſit at his door picking his teeth, and condemning the Capon he eat laſt, when alas poor deſpicable wretch! His throat is an abſolute ſtranger to ſuch dainty Viands; for a dried morſel of bread, hoary and cruſted with a ſecond bark, whoſe leather'd outſide would not court a dog arm'd with the edge of appetite, to eat it, would be adainty bit to cramb his empty gorge. Another will beg in this method: Firſt he looks to ſee whether the coaſt be clear, before he will utter one Suppliant ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, and then he approaches with ſuch ſubmiſſiveneſs, as a ſlave uſeth to his Patron; yet if any chance to glance that way with his eye, immediately he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats to familiarity, preſſing the juſtneſs of his demands, till he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121277:22"/>ſqueezes your Alms; which if it be a penny, or ſome ſuch incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſum (as they judge ſo ſmall a piece to be) he throws it contemptibly in the donors face; but ſoon after peaceably looks for it, finds it, and hath the grace to ſay an <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> or a <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> for the Benefactor. But now I think we have breath'd the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Courſer ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, let us turn our Bridle, and travel to <hi>Venice;</hi> which is taken to be no other then a Boat, that ſome Caſtle doth embarque by the Magick Laws of <hi>Urgandus,</hi> when he would have ſayled to great <hi>Albion</hi> to viſit <hi>Amadis,</hi> as he did in times of the year: and 'tis obſervable, that the world never produced ſuch unheard of <hi>Machiavilian</hi> Devices to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize an Enemy unawares, as the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121277:22"/>
               <hi>Venetian</hi> hath been Author of: for here you may ſee a Pocket Church-book, with a Piſtol hid in the binding, which turning to ſuch a page, diſcharges a plot to enſnare him to whom they bear a prejudice, whileſt at his Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when there is leaſt ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Execrable wretches! that make Gods Word the Cloak to palliate all their Villanies and Murthers.</p>
            <p>Another of their infernal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions is a pocket Stone-bow, which carried under a Cloak, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth Needles with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that it pierceth thorough a mans body and leaves a wound, whoſe Orifice is ſcarcely diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable by the moſt Eagle-ey'd Chyrurgion.</p>
            <p>A third, a Walking-ſtaff in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, at the top whereof is a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121277:23"/>ſpring, which graſpt hard, at the end jets forth a Rapier with force enough to kill a man at a yards diſtance.</p>
            <p>A fourth is a Gun, to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with wind, which for ſix paces fails not of execution, with little or no report. And give me leave to adde a fifth Knack of theirs, which is their <hi>Bergamaſque</hi> hanging up in the third Chamber of the Grand Dogues Gallery; being an Invention to lock up female frailty; an irrefragable Argument of the Italian Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, with which inhumane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint they do ſo perſecute and proſecute their Conſorts back and belly, and ſo cramp them hip and thigh, that if a poor deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Crab-louſe ſhould chance to be cloyſter'd up within theſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments, he hath not room to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121277:23"/>breath, and what would become of the poor Flea ſhould it be his fate to be thus confined? I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume he could not take his frol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likiſh Lavaltors. This Enginery of theirs manifeſts that they have a care of the hinder, not the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, altogether inſenſible of that old ſaying,
<q>
                  <hi>Felix quem faciunt aliorum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua cautum:</hi>
               </q> Surely thoſe men happy are, Whom others Horns make to beware.</p>
            <p>Yet I dare be bold to ſay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this rigid confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that no women of what nation ſoever, do oftner turn their Husbands back out of the Primmer into the Horn-book, or ſo often dub them Knights of <hi>Acteons</hi> order. As for the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian Ladies, when their ſtature
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121277:24"/>is promoted by the artifice of their <hi>Chiappines,</hi> they look like walking May-poles: And their faylings or fallings in the manner afore-mentioned (for they are moſt of them ſhe-Aſtrologers, and love to lye on their backs, contemplating on the Heavens, remembering what the Turks ſay, when they celebrate their nuptials, <hi>Look upon the Stars, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their number, and let that be an argument to induce you to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply:</hi>) 'Tis to be imputed to the too too much rigor of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts, and Parents: for the proof whereof let his enſuing Story ſatisfie you, taken out of their own Annals, and that of no meaner a perſon then the female iſſue of one of their gowned and grave Senators, who being cabled up by her Father from humane
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121277:24"/>ſight, and confined to the narrow round of a Chamber (then which no thing thwarts the grain of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male diſpoſition more; for they love to indulge their Genius, and have the ſwinge of their natural fancy) had a prodigious birth by her over-familiar Play-fellow, her Dog. To this ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical truth, give me leave to add a pretty ſtory of an ingenious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to a more ingenious Maſter, and that one of the Venetian Grandees; no other then the <hi>Magnificentiſsime Figlivolo di ſan Mario,</hi> who when his wife was ſick, and the Phyſician was to caſt her water, was at a loſs for a term to bid her make wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that might both ſuit with his dignity, and pleaſe her fine ears that were abſolute ſtrangers to ſuch a foul word, as <hi>piſſing:</hi> The
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121277:25"/>Grand Dogue being ſomewhat troubled, and wanting a Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to furniſh him with a word; his man reading his diſtemper in his face, deſired to be made ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the ſource of this his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, (for it was water that cauſed it) his Maſter to be rid of his importunate ſervant, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting any ſatisfaction from his tattle or endeavors, diſcloſes the buſineſs to him; which after he had done, he aſſures him that he would take it upon him, and find out a way to expreſs his minde by circumlocution, to ſignifie piſsing; which was thus: He boldly accoſts his Lady with the Urinal in his hand, ſaying, <hi>Chara Signora, fate quello che fate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanzi al cacare.</hi> I beſeech you, Madam, do that you uſe to do immediately before you ſh—
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121277:25"/>Pardon me Reader, if I offend thy noſtrils with this unſavory diſcourſe, for I have it onely by tradition, and you receive it from me, as I read it, ſo that it is the more excuſable, eſpecially in this Characteriſtical Treatiſe; But leſt we ſhould too too much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume upon your modeſty, we will leave <hi>Venice</hi> with this unſavory diſcourſe, and come to <hi>Padua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That reputed Nurſery of the Muſes, and Supportatrix of all Arts and Sciences: and here we muſt conſider their gowned Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which are ſo horribly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd, that we may ſafely ſay they ſtudy over the Bottle more then <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and mind their Plate more then their <hi>Plato,</hi> ſo much are they devoted to <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> that they could be content to turn Cyniques, ſo that with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121277:26"/>
               <hi>Diogenes</hi> they might dwell in the cask when the wine is exhauſted, and live by the ſent of that wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcored room for the future, nor would they deſire any other Tomb, than the Barrel; or at leaſt they could willingly entreat the Gods condemn them to ſuch a death, as the Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> had, <hi>viz.</hi> to be drowned in a But of Malmſey All the Rhetorick they ſtudy, is to perſwade the Vintner to credit them till the revolution of the Grand Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical year; nor do they imagine any Figure comparable to that of <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> to pay part for the whole. To drink beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure among them, is the higheſt of Sciences; falling backward is their ſtar-gazing; They delight in no muſick, but the ſweet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Good-fellowſhip, with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121277:26"/>now and then a diſcord. Wine is their Grammar; Sobriety a meer Solaeciſm, and to ſtudy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pericranium is elevated, is a prepoſterous <hi>heuſteron prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</hi> And when they ſtand in need of a Phyſician, a Receipt of full Cups (in their opinion) is the beſt Vomit; and forgetting of Debts, is their onely Art of Memory. They are <hi>Copernicans,</hi> and explode all ancient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Philoſophy, adhering ſolely to his Tenets; for they love to deal roundly with the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are never ſo well lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as when their heads run round: And thus could I expa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate upon their <hi>Encyclopaedia</hi> of Sciences, but that I fear in the deſcription of this Circulation, I ſhould prove eccentrique, and draw too long a line from the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121277:27"/>center of my intentions: But that which is more hainous, is, that Murther is ſo far from being counted a Venial Sin, that it is no Crime at all, as it ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by their neglect in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Offenders. Their mode is here, to go armed with a pair of Piſtols, and a Stilletto by their ſides<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'Tis ſtrange, methinks, to ſee <hi>Minerva</hi> ſo cloſely linked to <hi>Mars,</hi> to finde Students in ſuch a Warlike poſture: This cuſtom they ſay, proceeds from ſome old inbred Diſſention between the <hi>Vicentines</hi> and the <hi>Breſcians;</hi> which two contrary parties do ſo fill the ſtreets with ſlaughter, that no man can walke ſecurely at night for fear of their <hi>Chi va la:</hi> And which is a more notorious ſign of their Barbariſm, on the illars of the Porch or Arches,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121277:27"/>that run before the Houſe of this City, one may diſcern where Bullets have paſſed; nay, ſo tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial a buſineſs is <hi>Homicide</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, that if at any time they are deſtitute of a Body for the Anatomical Lecture, they make it a buſineſs of ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to kill a poor Fachin or Cobler, to exerciſe upon him by Diſſection, which proves that Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile of Learning to <hi>Scanderbeg's</hi> Sword, it either does much good or much hurt: for indeed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the School Axiom, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio optimi eſt peſsimae,</hi> The beſt Wine makes the ſharpeſt Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; and good wits once depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, uſually ſayl into an Ocean of Debauchery: And ſuch are they that have brought an odium upon <hi>Minerva's</hi> followers. But we will leave them and their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121277:28"/>Extravagancies, and ſtrike to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Genoa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which place 'tis proverbial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, <hi>That they have Mountains without wood, Sea without fiſh, Women without ſhame, and Men without Conſcience:</hi> and it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent that their haughtineſs hath given occaſion to thoſe that are leaſt critical to term it <hi>Genoa the proud.</hi> As to the nature and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Inhabitant, he is as lofty as his Building, ſo proud and gallant in his garb, that 'tis reported by thoſe that have been ſo unhappy as to travel there, that the firſt night of their arrival into this place, a company of Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ('tis a favour to call them ſo too) come to bid them Welcome with their muſick: but with ſo ſtately a Prologue, and ſo grave an Apology for themſelves, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121277:28"/>all the Gentlemen-ſtrangers withdrew from their Seats, and began to ſalute them, imagining them no leſs then Magiſtrates, or perſons of the higheſt degree. So that a Stranger may ſoon be deceived, as to their education, if unacquainted with their blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd inſolency. The moſt dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſpirit of them all is ſwell'd with the tympany of Pride: Who could ever imagine that ſuch inconſiderable fellows as they, that blow away their days in mirth, onely to procure a mean livelyhood, that are ſlaves to all company, ſhould be ſo ambitious, as to cloath their droſſy bodies in ſuch noble array: well may it be ſaid, that the bark is better then the tree, the external ſhew and pomp, then the internal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and ſolidity. They are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121277:29"/>all attired a like, ſomewhat tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Spaniſh mode, and of ſo haughty a ſpirit, that they will hardly condeſcend ſo far below themſelves, as to be aſſociates for ſtrangers. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> king of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon</hi> was often heard to have this expreſſion proceed from him <hi>Rex illiteratus eſt Aſinus corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus;</hi> An illiterate Prince, is but an Aſs crowned. But the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueſian Lady was of an opinion diametrically oppoſite unto it: ſo much did ſhe affect the prick of zeal, had the impudence to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm publickly, <hi>Penna non facit hominem, ſed Penis:</hi> Not the Pen but the P— qualifies a perſon: Could any one imagine a <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> ſo lecherous as to belch forth ſuch an expreſſion, as hath recorded her for a Lady of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; ſo ſtrange it is that it would
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121277:29"/>even ſtagger the faith of a Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidian to believe it, were it not inſerted in their own Annals, and nothing can carry a ſtronger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation with it, then what proceeds from their own mouths. But we will quit this obſcene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and pace it to <hi>Florence,</hi> to ſee what matter may be found there conducing to the perfecting of this Character.</p>
            <p>And we ſhall finde that for curious illegal tricks of Poyſon, they are damnably wicked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all compariſon. No Nation in the world ſo vindicative as they: They will poyſon with the ſmoke of a Candle, the ſmell of a Candle, or indeed any way imaginable; ſome of their poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are mortal by ſmelling, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers given now, may operate many moneths after; nay, 'tis
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121277:30"/>almoſt impoſsible to think that the depraved wit of man ſhould ever machinate ſuch damnable Devices for their mutual deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, unleſs they had received aſſiſtance from Hell. Some of them will attempt to poyſon whole Rivers, and not fail of their deſign, if they can finde out the ſource. And even to this day at <hi>Milan</hi> there ſtands a pillar that doth ſtigmatize them, call'd <hi>Colonna Infantae,</hi> raiſed where a Magicians houſe was pulled down, who for a time poiſoned all the Rivers belonging to the City; which ſtands ſtill as an everlaſting monument of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Infamy to them and their Heirs for ever. But leſt we ſhould be too much ſtung with this infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious diſcourſe, we will leave it, and ſeek for an Antidote in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily;</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:121277:30"/>but I fear the remedy will prove worſe then the Diſeaſe. 'Tis a Proverb that bears as much truth as antiquity in the front of it. <hi>Omnes Inſulanos eſſe malos, peſsimis verò Siculos.</hi> All Iſland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are bad, but the <hi>Sicilians</hi> are worſt of all. They are very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, and wavering like a Weather-cock, and you may as ſoon cut out a Kirtle for the Moon, as diſſwade them from their volatil humor; ſo that hence aroſe the Proverb, <hi>Gerra Sicula:</hi> Sicilian prittle-prattle, according to the pretty tattle of our infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Beſides, they are of a very envious, ſuſpicious, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive temper, uncapable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving an injury, and furiouſly vehement in the purſuit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, as appears by that great and inhuman maſſacre they made
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121277:31"/>of the French, known by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous name of <hi>Veſperi Siculi,</hi> where an infinite number of French were moſt barbarouſly butchered at the ſound of a Bell: An irrefragable Argument of their prepenſ'd malice, that would not allow them a ſufficient time time for Repentance. <hi>Pluto</hi> is deeply engaged to the <hi>Sicilian,</hi> and the <hi>Milaneze,</hi> for their true and faithful vaſſalage unto him; for it ſeems by all Hiſtory, that it is their ſole deſign to people his dominion, and adde as many ſlaves to his infernal Scepter as poſſibly they can. You have had an inſtance in the <hi>Sicilian,</hi> 'tis pity you ſhould want one of the helliſh <hi>Milaneze,</hi> who meeting a quondam friend of his in a place convenient for his barbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſign, and bearing him ſome
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121277:31"/>grudge, through the rancor of his ſpirit for ſome former, onely ſuppoſed injury offered unto him, ſet a knife to his throat, and bid him abjure God, or he would make him ſup with <hi>Pluto</hi> that very night, or if you will have it more plainly expreſſed, murder him, which the man attended with human frailty, (as all are,) and ſomewhat terrified at the name of death <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Philoſopher calls it, did; which after he had thrice done, he diſpatcled him, and like an inſulting Hell-hound immediatly after this execrable murther triumphed, ſaying, That he had ſent both ſoul and body to Hell with one fatal blow: Such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of inhumanity, what Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory can paralel? No nation under the Sun, in my judgement
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121277:32"/>can be ſo diabolical: But let us commit them, and all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to their Maſter, bellowing Belzeebub, who beyond all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverfie will in time pay them their wages.</p>
            <p>Now let us in general deſcant upon their Vices, and viſit firſt of all the Sun-bak't Peaſant in his rough-hewn-cottage, and we ſhall finde that he lives a drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlaviſh life, liable to all Gabels, Taxes, and Impoſitions from Superior Authority, in ſo much that 'tis proverbially ſaid: <hi>The Rich Men of</hi> Italy <hi>are the richeſt, and the Poor men the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the World.</hi> Excellent men they are, ſaid once an Hiſpanio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized Italian, but for theſe three things. In their luſts they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, in their malice unappea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeable, and in their actions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121277:32"/>To which let me adde a fourth, and a fifth; They will blaſpheme ſooner then ſwear, and murther ſooner then ſcandalize a perſon. 'Tis alſo an ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb of the people of <hi>Mazara, That they did build as if they ſhould live ever, and cram themſelves, as if they intended to live no longer:</hi> meer Epicures, that made this old Verſe their Motto:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lude, bibas, &amp; edas; poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem nulla voluptas.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Eat, drink, and play at leiſure;</l>
                  <l>For after death 's no pleaſure.</l>
               </q> Beſides, ſo contagious is this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that if a ſtranger begin once to fancy the place, ten thouſand to one if it change not his incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: 'Tis a Paradox to me, that the change of Air ſhould have ſo great an influence on the minde and conſtitution of man,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121277:33"/>were it not verified by ſeveral examples: Take this for one: A German Biſhop was ſo taken with their delicious Wine that grows about <hi>Monte Fiaſcone,</hi> that he ſent his ſervant to all the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns thereabout to finde out the beſt, and where he found it, to write over the door <hi>Eſt, Eſt;</hi> of which liquor he ſucked ſo much, and made a Tun of his Belly, German like, that he ſwam to the other world through an ocean of Wine: he was interred in <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonia's</hi> Church, and being a Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy man, 'tis pity his Tomb-ſtone ſhould want an Epitaph, and his memory conſume with the aſhes in his Urn, wherefore his ſervant made this ingenious Epitaph: <hi>Propter eſt, eſt, Dominus meus mortuus eſt:</hi> a Conceit no leſs fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetious than quipping; nay, 'tis a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121277:33"/>Proverb of their own, <hi>Tudeſco Italianato e un Diavolo incarnato:</hi> An Italianated German is a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil incarnal. 'Tis taken <hi>pro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo,</hi> that they have no leſs than twenty ſpecies of theſe intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting liquors to pleaſe the <hi>guſto</hi> at firſt, but carry their ſting in their tayles, fume up into the head, that though they are not immediately diſtemper'd, yet there is by their epotation laid the ſeed of all future maladies, that break to their enſuing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: The moſt delicious of all, which is their <hi>Ethnique Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctar,</hi> though they are ſo horribly blaſphemous, as to term it in a Chriſtian phraſe, <hi>Lachrymae Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti;</hi> which made one that had taſted, break out into this extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant paſſion, <hi>O Domine! cur non lachrymiſti in terris noſtris?</hi> O
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121277:34"/>Lord! why didſt thou not weep in our Countrey? That they are ambitious is apparent, for among the <hi>Vieentines</hi> 'tis an uſual Title for a Gentleman to be ſtyled <hi>Signor Conte,</hi> which is equivalent to <hi>My Lord</hi> with us: before they merit the degree of Knighthood, they muſt be Lorded. Not a Pedlar among them known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of <hi>Vueſtra Signioria;</hi> And for the Nobility, ſo mean they are, that according to their own Aſſertion (for I will bang them with their own weapons) <hi>I Marcheſi di Cova, I Conti di Piacenza, I Cavaglieri di Bolog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na:</hi> The Marquiſes of <hi>Ceva,</hi> the Lords of <hi>Piacenza,</hi> and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers, or Gentlemen of <hi>Bolog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> are grown poor, even to a Proverb.</p>
            <p>'Tis generally reported, that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121277:34"/>thoſe of <hi>Crema</hi> are deceitful, thoſe of <hi>Venice</hi> inſolent, the <hi>Genueſian</hi> proud, and the <hi>Paeln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinian</hi> lecherous: as for their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men it is grown to a Proverb among them, That they are Magpies at the door, Saints in the Church, Goats in the Garden, Divels in the Houſe, Angels in the Street, and Syrens at the window; Beſides 'tis an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſual expreſſion among them Let God make them tall and fall, (for the title of a comely woman is much prized among them) and they will make themſelves fair enough: But enough of that, their very Towns have by their judicious God-fathers been bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with names ſuitable to the nature of the inhabitants, as Genoa <hi>the proud,</hi> Piſtora <hi>the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barons,</hi> Perugia <hi>the bloody, babling</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:121277:35"/>Siena, <hi>and</hi> Furli <hi>the fantaſtick or wanton:</hi> They are all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral a heap of Fidlers, for you can ſcarce paſs a ſtreet, but you ſhall hear them rudely jarring, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtops, or time, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to <hi>Ge, Sol, Re, Ut,</hi> be it ſpoken, this harmony is made up of ſo much diſcord, that you would imagine it afar off to be a Conſort of Jackanapes's ſqueak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in rutting time. Yet I will not ſay they are ignoble, but they are the corrupters of nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: nor that they are illiterate, but the perverters of Learning: <hi>Martial</hi> and <hi>Juvenal</hi> amongſt them were famous, yet they were both obſcene: <hi>Perſius</hi> fooliſhly affected obſcurity, and would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in publique like an unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible Aſſe. <hi>Virgil</hi> himſelf ſuckt all his Poetick honey from the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121277:35"/>Hives of <hi>Homer, Theocritus,</hi> and other Greek Poets: And how much they reward the Learned will appear by that fate of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelphus</hi> the moſt accompliſhed perſon of his time, whoſe ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving friends were compell'd to ſell his Library at <hi>Bologna,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray the charges of his Funeral; ſo little do they minde or regard their Learned, though men of the moſt accute wit, and piercing underſtanding, perſons that might take the right hand of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the Vatican; 'tis a brand to the whole Nation upon record, that will never be conſumed by the iron teeth of Time, or huried in the grave of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> that they that are ſuch great preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Learning, and ſuch ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Ingenuity, as they would fain induce the world to believe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121277:36"/>them, ſhould be of ſuch a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick, baſe, ignoble, dunghil ſpirit, as not to defray his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Charges at the publick Coſt, but to make ſayl of his Books to that purpoſe: the conſideration hereof were enough to diſſwade Poſterity from ſtudy, and diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage men herafter from ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the purſuit of Learning, when their dead bodies ſhall not have decent Chriſtian Burial, though they promote the good and intereſt of the Republick wherein they live, by their inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable pains and induſtry, if their Coffers be not well lin'd, and they able to leave behinde them mountains of Gold, as well as the immortal Monuments of Wiſdom. Beſides, how do they encourage ingenious perſons, though they have the affluence
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121277:36"/>of all the goods of fortune? Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> who was indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Muſes for his fortune and preferment, when he came to the Popedom, being preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſeveral poetical pieces, return'd them this Dyſtych, in lieu of a recompenſation.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pro numeris numeros a me ſperate Poetae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carminaque eſt animus reddere, non emere.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Numbers for Numbers, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from me,</l>
                  <l>I do return, and not buy Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</l>
               </q> And though for oſtentation, and an outward ſhew of learning, they may ſtrike high with thoſe of their own ſtamp, yet if you reſpect the ſubſtance or ſolidity of learning, you ſhall finde but little among them; <hi>Muretus</hi> will
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121277:37"/>inform you as much, <hi>In mediâ Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liâ</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in medio Latio, in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diâ Greciâ, vix centeſimum quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> invenias, qui Latine aut Graecè lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui ſciat:</hi> In the middle of <hi>Italy, Latium,</hi> or <hi>Greece,</hi> you ſhal ſcarce finde one in a hundred that can underſtand either the Greek or Latine tongue. But you may be confident, they are ſo well train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in the School of Venery, that there is ſcarce a Peaſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, but hath <hi>Ovids Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> more perfect than their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Noſter;</hi> and can recount unto you how many obſcene poſtures there are in <hi>Aretine</hi> more readily then the number of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments in the Decalogue. Nay, many of their Popes, thoſe Princes of the Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth (as they are termed) are ſo illiterate, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121277:37"/>not to have the preferment of Servitors under an ingenious Junior Sophiſter; a poor Freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the Univerſity that ſcarce knows how many Colledges there are in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> would puzzle, if not put them to a <hi>non-plus</hi> with a Syllogiſm in <hi>Celarent. Paul</hi> the ſecond, who ſucceeded <hi>Aeneas</hi> in the Popedom, had a wicked deſign to demoliſh all Literature, and to extirpate all the Learned out of the Land, eſteeming all Students and Philoſophers no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Hereticks and Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; And 'tis grown into a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb among them, concerning thoſe that Commence among them, and travel thither on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be refin'd and better'd in learning, <hi>Nos accipimus pecuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; mittimus Aſinos in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniam:</hi> We receive Money
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121277:38"/>from you Germans, and ſend you a company of Aſſes in requital. This manifeſts the tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of his Sanctity, which it ſeems is ſo large, that <hi>Cromwel</hi> when he was alive, with all his Teem of Committee-men might be Canoniz'd by him; nay, I'le be bold to ſay it is ſo large, that a Countrey Waggon and ſix hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes might eaſily turn there; nay, they have entred ſuch villains in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Catalogue of Saints, that a Red-coat of their own (a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal I mean) uſed to ſay, <hi>Novi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hi Sancti de veteribus mihi dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um movent:</hi> Theſe new Saints of theirs, makes me begin to doubt of the old. And as the place of his Reſidence was firſt founded by Fugitives, Slaves, Thieves and Robbers, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards huddled up into an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121277:38"/>
               <hi>variis &amp; magnis latrociniis,</hi> by divers great Robberies, gained by oppreſſion, rapine, and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo ſhe may ſtill be ſaid to be a Harpye, and to cheat almoſt all the Chriſtian world with hermer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Pardons, Bulls, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences: what forceth them to beſtow ſuch bitter invectives, and ſcandalous Titles upon us, but onely becauſe we endeavor to pull down their pride and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, to deprive them of their external pomp and vanity? Nor had <hi>Luther</hi> ever been branded with the name of Apoſtate, had he ſtill adhered to their fond and Apiſh Superſtition: But what think you was the chiefeſt cauſe? No other but this, becauſe he took the Popes Mitre off of his head, and pull'd down the Monks bellies; down ſtomach, down,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121277:39"/>you had ne're been ſo high ſed, nor had ſuch good Commons, if he had been your Sewer: he was reſolv'd to preſcribe you a good, though mean Diet, and ſo keep you ſtill in health, whereas now you gorge your ſelves with varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of delicate Viands, ſo unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurably, that you may be ſaid to be <hi>animalia propter convivianata,</hi> brute beaſts calv'd onely to put in and put out. You are greatly devoted to the Goddeſs <hi>Cloaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and the God <hi>Stercutius,</hi> and grand Benefactors to <hi>T—T—</hi> the Scavenger. Now Reader, take this enſuing Story for an Argument and Proof of their gluttony and exceſs, though it be quite contrary to their function, who ought to check and curb their ſenſual appetites, yet they do the quite contrary: It is chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicled
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121277:39"/>of one of our Kings, that having bin hunting with ſome of his Nobles a conſiderable time, and ſomewhat tyred at the ſport, ſtrayed from the Game, and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his thirſt to be great, and his ſtomach to have ſtrook twelve, reſolved to make to the next houſe to refreſh himſelf with ſome Victuals or other that the place could afford; which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to be a Monaſtery, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into he enters, calls for the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot, &amp; deſireshim to give him the accommodation of the houſe how mean ſoever it were; he looking ſtedfaſtly on him, ſoon diſcerned by his countenance that he was ſome perſon of quality, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he preſented him with a piece of Roaſt Beef, a Capon, and ſome other Joynts of Meat, making a large Apology withal
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121277:40"/>for the meanneſs of the Fare, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring him it was <hi>prater ſolitum</hi> for them to be ſo poorly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The King fell too't, for he had a coming ſtomach, and plyed it tooth and nayl, withal admiring that the Monaſtery ſhould be accuſtomed to ſuch variety, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining before they had liv'd very penuriouſly, according to their profeſſion; then he ruminated on the Abbots excuſe, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt him with a conceit that they uſed to feed upon more dainty Cates: and that that mov'd him to this opinion moſt of all, was the Abbots ſaying, Lord Sir, I do very much admire how you can feed ſo heartily upon ſuch home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meat; I could not eat of ſuch mean fare, I promiſe you: The King return'd him no anſwer till he was ſatisfied, but then he gave
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121277:40"/>him very many thankes for his noble Entertainment, and ſo took his leave of him and departed, reſolving to make them change their dyet, and not cram them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Capons that are to be kill'd; and with theſe thoughts he paſs'd away the time till he met with his Attendants, who were all very much aſtoniſh'd at his long abſence, but he gave them no account at all of what had paſs'd; but the next day ſent a Meſſenger with a command to bring the Abbot before him, which accordingly was executed, and he appeared: The King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to relate unto him the whole ſtory, and how that he was the perſon he miſtook for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Gentleman, withal checking him for his luxury, promiſing that he would make him feed on roaſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121277:41"/>Beef ere he had done, and ſay it was excellent good fare too, and ſo commanded him to be taken into cuſtody, and be ſecured in the Tower; which accordingly was done, and he to remain there the ſpace of three days without any natural ſuſtenance; at the end of the third day the King ſends to know, whether or no Beef would go down yet: O Sir, replied the Abbot, Roaſt Beef or any thing, Roaſt Beef or any thing; ſo according to the Kings order, a piece of a cold Loin of Beef was ſent him, upon which he fed very heartily; which the King hearing, he immediately Knighted that Joynt of Meat, ſo that is called <hi>A Sir-loin</hi> to this very day. His Majeſty it ſeems was reſolv'd to allow him but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le dyet, till he heard that his nice
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121277:41"/>curioſity had left him; 'twas too groſs and heavy meat for his ſqueamiſh ſtomach, during his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence in the Monaſtery, but when tranſplanted from thence to the Tower, 'twas the beſt piece of meat that ever he exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed his teeth upon. But we muſt not hit him in the teeth too much with it, therefore wee'l proceed to another ſtory of the ſordid Covetouſneſs of a fat bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied Popiſh Prieſt among them: there was an old <hi>Sybil,</hi> one Goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Tully</hi> by name, who had ſadled her prognoſticating Noſe with a pair of <hi>Amſterdams</hi> Spectacles, at this very time 60 years, &amp; better; this old Adage knowing that ere long ſhe ſhould be one of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerpina's</hi> fold, began to conſider her end, and reſolved to make her laſt Will and Teſtament, her
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121277:42"/>houſhold-ſtuff was but little and mean, for ſhe had nothing but a pot, a ſtool, a bed, and a candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, beſides a vexatious Hen that played ſuch miſchievous tricks, as fretted the old woman to the ſoul, and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c'd her to theſe paſſionate expreſſions oftentimes <hi>Pox take thee, The devil take thee;</hi> But ſhe being, as I told you, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to expire, did in her Will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath this Hen to the Prieſt, which he, as ſoon as he heard of, before the old womans death, came and fetcht away; which being related to her, ſhe played the wag upon her death-bed, and cried, I have bid the Pox take her, and the Devil take her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, but 'twas to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but I bid the Prieſt take her but once, and he hath fetcht her from me; nay, without doubt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121277:42"/>if he can get any thing once with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his clutches, you may as ſoon perſwade a Genevan to turn Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, as to talk it out of him: There is no redemption from hell, they ſay, nor is there a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of recovering any thing from theſe helliſh Prieſts, when once in their own poſſeſſion, they are extraordinary good at Hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and will as ſoon lay hold of a promiſe, as any men upon the earth. Theſe are their pious ſouls, devout devils, they are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to exorciſe evil ſpirits, and they had need be caſt out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But we ſhall not yet quite caſt them out of minde, for we muſt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other bout with them, and manifeſt their ſimplicity to be as great, as their irreligion is hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and that thus: A certain
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121277:43"/>Fryar being on Pilgrimage to ſome of their Saints, or Ladies, ('tis no matter which of them) being ſomewhat wearied with his hard travel, took up a Lodging for his little youth and himſelf for that night, reſolving there to pitch his tents, and to walk no farther till the next morning. It ſeems in the night he was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a dream that did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb him much more awake then aſleep, which he muſt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to his Boy (he was a wiſe man the while you muſt imagine) and it was this: That he dreamt he was kiſſing his own Breech, (and that is the way to break his own neck all the world knows) ſo calling his little Lad to him, cold him, that he dreamt he kiſs't his own Breech; I but Maſter, ſaith the Lad, as nimbly as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121277:43"/>dreams always prove con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, you muſt kiſs mine; He it ſeems muſt be the <hi>Arte midorus</hi> to interpret his dream, and he did it to ſome purpoſe: Here was old kiſſing between them both, yet the Fryar had had the worſt on't which way ſoever it had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, his little Lacquey quite out-witted him.</p>
            <p>How excellently learned they are will appear, if you conſider their inſight in the Latin tongue; for a Prieſt being put once to conſtrue a ſentence out of <hi>Tullius de Officiis,</hi> that is known to every School-boy in his <hi>Corderius,</hi> and it was this, <hi>Indutus toga virili,</hi> which he turned thus: <hi>Indutus,</hi> having put on, <hi>toga virili,</hi> his green Gown: He thought ſurely he was tumbling with the luſty ſanguine complexion'd Girls in a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121277:44"/>green meadow, or elſe he could never have hit of ſuch a tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Another being demanded by one of our Clergy men in <hi>England,</hi> how many Sacraments there were? replied, Nine: at which he being amazed, he asked him how he could prove it: to which he rejoyn'd, ſeven beyond ſea, and two with you: at which the Biſhop ſmiling, though pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ignorance, diſmiſſed him. One more inſtance I have for you, and then I have done: A certain Prieſt among them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often to viſit a Merchant, one of his Pariſhioners, becauſe he was one of his nobleſt Benefact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, was ſo much taken with his Wife, that for the future he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to aſſociate himſelf with the Miſtreſs, and not the Maſter of the Houſe, which accordingly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121277:44"/>he did, and ſollicited her inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly for a nights lodging (ſee what it is to be troubled with the Pr— of zeal) but ſhe like a chaſte Matron, ſcorning to be diſloyal to her husband, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> Lady had been ſo loyal, <hi>Nol</hi> had ne're made him wear the Bulls Feather) and withal ſhe did inculcate, and repeat the ſcandal that it was to thoſe of his Coat, to entertain ſo much as a thought of coveting his neighbors wife; but he a ſervant to the fleſh more then to the ſpirit, grew the more earneſt for being repuls'd, and renewed his intreaties and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions with more vigor, then formerly: She perceiving it was impoſſible to avoid it, unleſs it were by diſcovering him, reſolv'd to do it when her husband came home; which accordingly ſhe did,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121277:45"/>who after he underſtood his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, bid her promiſe him the uſe of her body, and he would be in the next room ready to enter in the very heighth of opportunity, and ſpoil his ſport; ſo the next time he came, he perſiſted ſtill in his accuſtomed humor, and ſhe at laſt with a kinde of unwilling willingneſs, ſeemed to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with his perſwaſions, and ſo conſented to let him have the fruition of his deſire, which he over-joyed to hear, made all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſpeed to the Bed-chamber, where in the twinkling of a Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaff, he diſrob'd himſelf of his Pontificalibus, and was juſt skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping into bed, when her husband rattled at the door, which ſhe hearing, bid him get into the Preſs that ſtood by the Bed ſide, to hide himſelf; which he did in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121277:45"/>all haſte, glad at his heart that he was cloyſter'd within thoſe woodden walls from the ſight of the Goodman of the houſe, who coming in in the interim, taking no notice at all of the buſtle he made with tumbling into the Preſs; How doſt thou, my dear? ſaith he, Prethee what's the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that this Preſs is always left open? and ſo lockt it, and put the Key in his Pocket: Now you muſt note by the way, that this fell out to be on Saturday night, as fortune would have it, and the Prieſt, next morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sunday, was to officiate in the Pulpit; the day began at the length to appear, and the time draw nigh wherein people uſually frequent the Temple, there all ſervice was perform'd, the Saints<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell rung, and the people gaping
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121277:46"/>in expectation of the Prieſt, who as yet was cabinetted up in the Merchants houſe, who had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign upon him to make him a publick example of infamy to the people, and ignominious and hateful to the Clergy, at leaſt in appearance and outward ſhew, (though they can paſs by ſuch tricks of youth without exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or puniſhment) which was this, he cauſed the Preſs to be carried into the Church, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced behinde the Pulpit, at which ſudden and unexpected ſight the Congregation was amazed, and immediately gave order that the Preſs door ſhould be opened; which was no ſooner done, but the Prieſt like a ghoſt newly come from among the tombs, ſteps into the Pulpit with theſe words in his mouth, <hi>Sic reſurrexit</hi> Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121277:46"/>
               <hi>è ſepulchro:</hi> In this poſture did <hi>Lazarus</hi> ariſe out of the grave, and preacht upon't as his Text; for which his religious zeal, he was highly extoll'd by the people (they being altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of his luſty zeal that firſt cauſed his confinement) and the Merchant perceiving how inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly he had cloaked this his piece of knavery, did not divulge it at that preſent, but kept it within his own breaſts: But we muſt not ſcratch the pates of theſe bald Prieſts too much, leſt we draw blood: now to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſt. The Canon-Law that hath ſo great a vogue in <hi>Italy,</hi> will ſooner be condemn'd for vicious, then extoll'd for juſt, when you conſider that it makes the Crown do homage to the Mitre; the Scepter to the Croſier, and the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121277:47"/>Emperors Throne to the Popes Chair.</p>
            <p>Among the Italians he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted no leſs then a fool, that is not melancholy once a day: They are onely liberal to their Superiors, from whom they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect greater benefits; to all others the purſe is cloſeſt ſhut, when the mouth opens wideſt: nor is there any probability of your get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a piece of Cake there, unleſs yours be known to be in the Oven. To add to their treaſure, they will light a candle to the Devil. In <hi>Legorn</hi> they allow a Jews Synagogue; nay, you may be what Devil you will there, ſo you puſh not the Pope with your horn. They are the greateſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracers of pleaſure, and eſteem of pearles as pebles, ſo they can but ſatiate their <hi>Guſto,</hi> in point
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121277:47"/>of pleaſure, Here you may finde Love and Hatred, Virtue and Vice, Superſtition, and Religion in their extreams, for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt wits once depraved prove ever the moſt dangerous. They are in their Luſts unnatural, in their hatred irreconciliable, and in their thoughts unfathomable, ſo that with one breath they blow both hot, and cold, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs their own ends, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their own deſignes, they will play the Divel incarnat: But now we will wring them no more by the noſe, leſt we fetch blood, wherefore we will allay the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs of this potion with the edulcorating ingredients of their virtues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Italy</hi> is the Garden of <hi>Europe,</hi> the Terroir being gentle and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, and produceth a more
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121277:48"/>ſtately crop, then the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man oft-times expects: and ſome Soyls there are, that afford four Latter-meaths of Hay and Graſs: For their delicious wines no Countrey can paralel it, beſides it excels in large and ſtately Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, nor is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> altogether improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that ſhe receive her name therefore from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Calf: The fame of the <hi>Neapolitan Courſier</hi> hath run through all the habitable world: for the number and luſtre of Nobility, no nation exceeds them, which makes moſt ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits tranſported with the deſire of viſiting her Territories: As for the ingenuity and dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the inventive brain of the Italian, if you reſpect either Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers or Opificers, all Nations have been benefited thereby; nay
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121277:48"/>they have been almoſt adored by by the reſidue of the Europian part of the world.</p>
            <p>For all ſpeculative and theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick Sciences, the Italian equal moſt Nations under the heavens, as may appear by the almoſt infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of Wits that ſhe hath nurſed, as <hi>Virgil, Eunius; Lucrece, Statius, Plantus,</hi> for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Poetry; for according to the Stagirite, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Poeſie is a divine thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Prudence in the Law, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat, Pancirolus, Peregrinus,</hi> and <hi>Hondaus,</hi> were very famous.</p>
            <p>In the Secreſies and Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Medicine, none could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel <hi>Fracaſtorius, Matthiolus, Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopius, Aldrovandus, Johannes Baptiſta Porta,</hi> and <hi>Talicotius,</hi> who could imitate Nature even to admiration, in making artificial
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121277:49"/>Noſes, Eares, and Eyes.</p>
            <p>For Hiſtory, <hi>Francis Guiceiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Bembo, Vergerius, Magirus, Cardan, Picus</hi> Earl of <hi>Mirandula, Zabaralla,</hi> and <hi>Urſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> veyl to none for Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</p>
            <p>Nor hath <hi>Mercury</hi> onely his Seminary here, but <hi>Mars</hi> hath his Standard alſo, being very exact in the Rules of Military Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and excellent Engineers: And as to Treaty, never did any Nation come near him, he was never out-witted that way.</p>
            <p>She hath produced many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sons of <hi>Mars,</hi> as <hi>Scaliger</hi> Prince of <hi>Verona, Caſtruccio, Sforza,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſia Spinola;</hi> as alſo <hi>Alexander Farneſe</hi> Duke of <hi>Parma.</hi> They are excellent Navigators; 'twas <hi>Americo Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpucio</hi> a Florentine, that baptized
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121277:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>the new world; And <hi>Chriſtophero Columbo,</hi> which acts of his all paſt Ages cannot equal, and he onely by the dexterity of his wit and inſight of the Mathematicks, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it.</p>
            <p>Nor are her Cities leſs famous then her inhabitants: and firſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is judged the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſs of the world, the Protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ereſs of all Arts and Sciences, and the Fountaine from whoſe ſtreams of Virtue and Piety, the reſt of the Chriſtian world is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. 'Twas the cordial wiſh of that Father of the Fathers of the Latine Church <hi>St. Auguſtine,</hi> that he might compaſs the ſight of three things. Our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the Fleſh, St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the Pulpit, and <hi>Rome</hi> in her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt flouriſh, and the meridian of her glory. Give but an ear to what
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121277:50"/>
               <hi>Martial</hi> the Epigrammatiſt ſings, as her due Encomium.
<q>
                  <hi>Terrarum Dea, Gentium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Roma Cui par eſt nihil, &amp; nihil ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi>
               </q> What a vaſt Circumference ſhe had, may be gueſſed at by the number of Cobwebs that <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabalus</hi> cauſed to be gathered there, which amounted to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand weight.</p>
            <p>As for the renown'd Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> without her, as an eminent Author of our times notes, <hi>Italy</hi> ſhould want her chiefeſt Ornament, Liberty a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, <hi>Europe</hi> her Bulwark, <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> ſhould be deſtitute of a Miſtris, and Nature of a Miracle. She is a Lady that hath encroacht more upon <hi>Neptunes</hi> dominions, then any State in the World: She commands a fortreſs that is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121277:50"/>built according to the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act rules of Enginery, that ſtood her in two millions the erecting, and charges her with a hundred thouſand Crowns <hi>per annum,</hi> her yearly maintenance. Her Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal is as famous a wonder as her illuſtrious ſelf, ſhe would extaſy a foreiner with the ſight of her ſtately fabricks. This City, ſaith one of our well-worded Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, that is adorn'd with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion of Parts, and Arts, Manners, and Manors, hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a Virgin nere upon theſe fifteen hundred years, yet withal ſuch an Amazon, that ſhe hath wreſtled with the moſt potent Monarchs in <hi>Europe,</hi> and thrown ſome of them flat on their backs, but none of them could lay her in ſuch a poſture, as to get her Mayden-head. Her grandees are
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121277:51"/>noble Patriots, <hi>Patres Patriae,</hi> they have publique ſpirits, are fage in Councels, and ſolid in their judgement, conſtant in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and moderate in good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: Nor doth her incolumity depend upon the ſlender twiſt of the life of one ſingle perſon, but upon the prudent management of an immortal Senate.</p>
            <p>The Characters that the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned confer upon her are many, noble, and what ſhe deſerves in their own judgement. <hi>Mamerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the Panegyriſt, calls her <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Dominam,</hi> the Miſtreſs of all Nations. <hi>Rutilius Numatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Coeleſtem mundique Reginam;</hi> A Heavenly thing, and Empreſs of the world. <hi>Dionyſius Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſaeus, Totius Orbis optimam:</hi> The moſt famous Countrey in the whoſe univerſe. And others,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121277:51"/>
               <hi>Caput Orbis,</hi> The Head of the world, and that not undeſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for either Pike or Pen, <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> or <hi>Mars;</hi> no Nation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever that comes into the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with her, but will be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiz'd, if held up by an unbyaſſed hand.</p>
            <p>Touching her Exceſſes, and principally thoſe of the Popes, which have been ſufficiently ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomized by ſeveral Authors, it is incontrovertible; that among ſo great a number ſome will be found culpable: There is no Wheat, but ſome Chaff; no Wine but ſome Lees. In the firſt Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that our bleſſed Saviour made, among twelve there was one found bad: But let it not be buried in oblivion, that the firſt thirty three Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Martyrdom: And if that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121277:52"/>the Eccleſiaſticks Purple ſeem to dazzle the eyes of ſome weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted, and ſlenderly-grounded perſons, and that the Clergy ſeem to them to lead a life in too much external pomp and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward glory, the Capuchians frock and the recluſe and auſtere lives of Mendicant Fryars, and other abſtenious perſons, may ſerve in lieu of an Apology for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Extravagancies.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Naples</hi> be cramm'd with Courtizano's, yet the chaſtity of ſo many thouſands of pious cloyſter'd ſouls, who have totally wean'd themſelves from all mundane frothy delights, and adhered to heaven, and the hopes they have of the fruition thereof, may make ſome ſatisfaction for their Exceſſes. But <hi>Scaurus</hi> hath penned among his Works a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121277:52"/>that deſerves conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that is, <hi>Non minus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam virtutem eſſe ſcire deſinere, quam ſcire dicere.</hi> It is no leſs vertue to know when to put a period to a Diſcourſe, then to write the Exordium; wherefore I judge it far better to ſtrike ſayl, then to launch any farther into ſo vaſt an Ocean of Matter, as the Praiſe of the <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alians:</hi> Thus having bid adieu, I make an</p>
            <trailer>END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:53"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books to be ſold by</hi> Nath Brook <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THe accompliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Cook, the Myſtery of the whole Art of Cookely revealed in a more eaſie and perfect Method then hath been publiſhed in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. By <hi>Robert May</hi> in the time of his attendance on ſeveral Perſons of Honor.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>J. Cleaveland</hi> Revived: Poems, Orations, Epiſtles, and other of his Genuine Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pieces: A ſecond Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with many Additions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Exquiſite Letters of Mr. <hi>Robert Loveday,</hi> the late ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Tranſlatour of the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the famed Romance <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> for the perpetuating his memory; publiſhed by his dear Brother, Mr. <hi>A. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:53"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Englands</hi> Worthies: Select Lives of the moſt Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, to the death of <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> late Protector: By <hi>Wil. Winſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A Character of <hi>France:</hi> to which is added <hi>Gallus Caſtratus;</hi> or, an Anſwer to a late ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pamphlet, called, <hi>The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of</hi> England; as alſo a freſh Whip for the Mounſieur, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his Letter, in vindication to his Madam, the ſecond Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>William Clowes</hi> his Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Obſervations for thoſe that are burned with flames of Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, as alſo for the curing of wounds, and of the <hi>Lues vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Saints Happineſs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſeveral ſteps lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:121277:54"/>thereunto, delivered in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Lectures on the <hi>Beatitudes,</hi> contained in the 5th of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew:</hi> By <hi>Jeremiah Burroughs</hi> late Preacher of <hi>Stepney.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. His Goſpel-Revelation, in three Treatiſes: 1. Of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God. 2. Of the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Chriſt 3. Of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of mans Immortal Soul. By the ſame Author.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121277:54"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
